Guide to the Vi Fogle Uretz Papers 1930-2003
University of Chicago Library
Uretz, Vi Fogle. Papers
1930-2003
18.5 linear feet (19 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
This collection contains the papers of Vi Fogle Uretz (1916-2007), a University of Chicago alumna, artist and community activist. The collection includes material related to the organization of the 57th Street Art Fair and the threatened closure of the university's International House. Also included are samples of Uretz's artwork, such as sketches and photographs of urban renewal in Hyde Park.
Information on Use
Access
Series III contains videocassettes and audio tapes that are restricted due to re-formatting and equipment requirements.
The remainder of the collection is open for research, with no restrictions.
Biographical Note
Vi Fogle Uretz (1916-2007) was a University of Chicago alumna, wife of faculty member Robert B. Uretz, and an active member of the Hyde Park community. She was involved in many community organizations, including the radio station WFMT, the Hyde Park Historical Society, the 57th Street Art Fair, and the Cleaner Air Committee. As an artist, Uretz exhibited her paintings and sketches across the United States, as well as locally at the 57th Street Art Fair. Within the Hyde Park community, Uretz documented changes to the landscape of the city during urban renewal through her paintings, sketches and photographs.
Scope Note
This collection contains the papers of Vi Uretz and is divided into three series, each organized alphabetically.
Series I: Community Activities, contains materials related to Uretz's involvement with local organizations and events. Included here is information on the 57th Street Art Fair, highlighting the development of the 50th anniversary book, as well as materials from 57th Street Art Fair founder Mary Louise Womer. Boxes 1, 2, and 3 contain oversized materials relating to the Art Fair, including posters, photographs, and book layout pages. This series also contains information concerning University of Chicago events such as lectures, exhibits, and the threatened closure of the International House in 2000. Box 10 contains oversized materials relating to the University, including visual art information and a scrapbook.
Series II: Family, contains the late-nineteenth century correspondence of Agnes Seely, a relative of Uretz.
Series III: Artwork and Audio-Visual Materials, contains reproductions of Uretz's illustrations and a small number of originals, as well as photographs and slides of urban renewal in Hyde Park. This series also contains videocassette tapes of artwork and interviews for a documentary made for the 50th anniversary of the 57th Street Art Fair. Boxes 17 and 18 contain oversized materials, including slides and sketches relating to urban renewal.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
57th Street Art Fair. Records
Subject Headings
Uretz, Vi Fogle; 57th Street Art Fair (Chicago, Ill.); Urban renewal -- Illinois -- Chicago; Artists -- Illinois -- Chicago; Women artists
INVENTORY
- Series I: Community Activities
  - 57th Street Art Fair, posters, 1978-1999 (Box 1)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary book layout pages with photographs, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, photographs by Nancy Hays, 1965-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, posters and press clippings, 1950-2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, photographs omitted from the 50th anniversary book, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 1973-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary, book information, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary, book, planning materials, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary, book, proofs and final, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary, book revisions, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 50th anniversary, book, source material, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, list of volunteers, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, newspaper clippings, 1958-2001 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, research for 50th anniversary book, 1948-1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - African Festival, supplement, Chicago Tribune, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chicago community groups, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cleaner Air Committee, 1958-1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Greene-Mercier, book by Frank Elgar, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Greene-Mercier, Marie Zoe, correspondence, information and artwork, 1971-1996 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Hyde Park Historical Society, newsletters, event information, 1984- 2003 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Hyde Park Historical Society, urban renewal, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hyde Park history, 1950-2002 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Medicine on the Midway, magazine, 1994-2002 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Publications, 1982-1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - University of Chicago calendars, 1989-2003 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - University of Chicago, catalogues of exhibitions held in Special Collections, 1977-2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, Brown, Edward, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, Chabala, Jan, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, "Challenges in Imaging," 1998 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, "Invasions in Particle Physics," 2001 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, Kessler, Richard, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, notes, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, Pryke, Clem, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - University of Chicago, Compton lecture series, Ries, Harold, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - University of Chicago, Court Theatre, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, International House, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, Chicago Business, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, Chicago Maroon, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, Chicago Maroon, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, Chicago Weekly News, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, Hyde Park Herald, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - University of Chicago, International House, newspaper articles, University of Chicago Chronicle, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago Magazine, 1985-1997 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago Oriental Institute, publications, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago Presents, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago publications, 1960-2001 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - University of Chicago publications, history, 1982-2000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago and Hyde Park, visual art information, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago, "A Place Where the Remarkable Happens," n.d. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - University of Chicago, scrapbook, 1935-1938 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago Renaissance Society, 1980-2003 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - University of Chicago Renaissance Society, material, 1934-2001 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - University of Chicago, the Smart Museum of Art, 1974-2002 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Visual art, exhibitions and articles, 1977-1998 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Visual art information, University of Chicago and Hyde Park, 1974- 1997 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Washington travel information, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Womer, John Robert, notes, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, 1941-1996 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, 50th anniversary cards, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, art notes and information, 1964-1991 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, artists, 1959-1993 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, auction and memorial service, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, California artists, 1938-1995 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, Chicago Historical Society, annual reports, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, correspondence, 1950-1980 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, exhibition calendars, 1950-1965 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, gifts to Chicago Historical Society, 1979-1991 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, Hyde Park Fine Art, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Womer, Mary Louise and John, photograph, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, list of art fair poster designers, 1948-1997 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "Womer and McCartney, Movies and Videos," 1996 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Womer, Mary Louise (nee Clifton), MFA thesis, "Folk Art of the Ozarks," 1941 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, papers, 1948-1995 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, reading group and contacts, 1994-1995 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, receipts from art purchases, 1966-1979 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Series II: Family
  - Biographical data on Agnes Seely, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Agnes Seely, 1865-1880 (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, Agnes Seely, 1865-1880 (Box 14, Folder 1-6)
- Series III: Artwork and Audio-Visual Materials
  - 57th Street art fair, interviews and artwork for documentary on 50th anniversary, videocassette tapes, 1999-1997 (Box 15)
  - 57th Street Art Fair, 30th anniversary talk at Hyde Park Art Center, audiocassette tape, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Artistic reproductions, prints, photographs, and magazine clippings, 1930-1940 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Specimen type faces of historic interest, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - University of Chicago campus, photographs, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - University of Chicago, former Deans of Biological Sciences, photographs n.d. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - University of Chicago, Harper Library, photographs, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - University of Chicago, Learning Center, photographs, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - University of Chicago, Mitchel Hospital construction, photographs, 1982 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Urban renewal, clippings of sketches, circa 1957 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Urban renewal in Hyde Park, slide show for the Hyde Park Historical Society, audiocassette tape, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Urban renewal, new town homes construction, demolition, moving signs, photo negatives, 1957-1964 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Urban renewal, demolition of Hyde Park, slides, 1957-1958 (Box 17)
  - "Urban Renewal 3," sketch, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "Urban Renewal 4," sketch, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Urban renewal, photographs, 1956-1957 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Urban renewal, photographs as seen for 5529 Dorchester, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Urban renewal, photographs and slides of demolition of church and hotel, 1957-1971 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - "Urban Renewal", sketch, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Urban renewal, sketch, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Urban renewal, sketch, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - "Urban Renewal 5," sketch, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - "Urban Renewal 6," sketch, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - "Urban Renewal 49," sketch, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - "Urban Renewal 65," sketch, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Urban renewal, "Brick Pickers," sketch, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Urban renewal, "Demolition of Kenwood Gardens 2," 1957 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Urban renewal, view looking west toward 5500 block of Kenwood Ave., sketch, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Urban renewal, University of Chicago Magazine, November 1957 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Womer, John, memorial service, audiocassette tape, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Womer, Mary Louise, videocassette tapes, 1985-1998 (Box 19, Folder 16)